A Guide to the Lee-Jackson Collection WLU.Coll.0170
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Lee-Jackson Foundation Collection
1847-1905
Bulk dates 1847-1869
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Maury, Matthew Fontaine
Lee-Jackson Foundation
Maury, Richard S.
Lee, Mary Randolph Custis, 1807-1883
Lee, George Washington Custis
Lossing, Benson J. (Benson John)
Wise, Henry
Cocke, Preston
Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh, 1837-1891
Lee, Robert E., Jr., 1843-1914
Cocke, Edmund R.
Lee, Charles Carter
Lee, Richard Henry
Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893
Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston), 1807-1891
Hallowell, Benjamin
Kerr, Charles
Hotchkiss, Jedediah, 1828-1899
Preston, Margaret Junkin
Lee, Mildred Childe, 1846-1905
Lee, Agnes
WLU.Coll.0170
118 Item
Online Access
View materials from this collection online via W&L's Digital Archive
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lee-Jackson Foundation of Charlottesville, Va.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists 115 total items. Box one consists of eighty-six letters written by members of the Lee Family of Virginia, including Robert E. Lee; his wife, Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee; his children, his father-in-law, George Washington Parke Custis; and Lees of the 18th through early 20th century. Box two consists of twenty-nine items, most written by and/or received by individuals connected to the Lee and/or Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson military and family circles. Prominent military officers represented include Joseph E. Johnston, Elisha Franklin Paxton, Edward Johnson, Daniel Harvey Hill, and Winfield Scott. While some letters from this collection concern public matters during the American Revolution, the Civil War and the post-Civil War South, many are of domestic and personal nature.
The sixteen R.E. Lee items cover a date span of 22 years from 1847 through 1869. There are ten letters of Mrs. Mary Randolph Custis Lee ranging from the early 1850s to shortly before her death in 1873.
Correspondence; Mexico; American Confederate voluntary exiles; Confederate States of America; Lee-Jackson Foundation
- Letters, 1775-1903 (Box 1)
  - Robert E. Lee to "My dear Major", 1847-02-28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Robert E. Lee to Joseph G. Totten, 1853-01-06 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert E. Lee to William J. Clarke, 1861-10-11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Robert E. Lee to Major Harman, 1862-04-18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Robert E. Lee to "My dear Madame", 1862-09-23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert E. Lee to Isaac Trimble, 1863-03-21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert E. Lee to Gov. John Letcher, 1863-10-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Robert E. Lee to Richard Ewell, 1864-05-10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Robert E. Lee to Mrs. Margaret B. Daingerfield, 1865-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Robert E. Lee to Richard S. Maury, 1865-07-31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Robert E. Lee (circular letter) from Near Cartersville, 1865-07-31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Robert E. Lee to Matthew Fontaine Maury, 1865-09-08; Maury, Matthew Fontaine; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    In this letter From Cartersville, Va, Lee writes to Maury that he is disappointed in the government but that he wants to continue trying to make it better. He advises Maury against his ideas about starting a settlement of ex-Confederates and other immigrants. A transcription of this letter is housed with the original.
  - Robert E. Lee to Richard S. Maury, 1865-09-11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robert E. Lee to Major W. I. Hawks, 1866-01-08 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Robert E. Lee to John W. Truslow, 1868-03-07 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Robert E. Lee to Dr. A. G. Bledsoe, 1869-05-15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Printed funeral announcement re Robert E. Lee, 1870-10-15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agnes Lee to Mrs. Richard L. Maury, 1867-01-14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Alfred Lee to N. Burwell, 2 notes (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Alfred Lee to N. Burwell, 1852-02-10v
    - Alfred Lee to N. Burwell, N.D.
  - Arthur Lee -- court copy of his will made on 1792-07-07, 1803-08-26 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Arthur Lee printed copy of his, "An Appeal to the Justice and Interests of the People of Great Britain, in the Present Disputes with America", 1775 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Charles Lee to Joseph Nourse, 1791-10-10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Charles Lee to James McHenry, 1801-11-28 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Charles Lee to William A. Washington, 1802-09-28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Charles Carter Lee to Nat Burwell, 1848-02-01 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Charles Carter Lee to Nat Burwell, 1848-06-25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Charlotte W. Lee to Nat Burwell, 1853-04-30 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Edmund Jennings Lee to Alexander Brown, 1892-10-11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Edmund Jennings Lee to Alexander Brown, 1892-10-22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Edmund Jennings Lee to "My dear Sir", 1892-12-30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Francis Lightfoot Lee to "My dearest", 1780-07-05 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to "General", 1865-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fitzhugh Lee, Received of Charles Kerr, 1875-11-11 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr, 1877-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr, 1877-10-09 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr, 1877-10-24 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie G. Kerr, 1878-12-27 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Mr. Warfeild, 1880-01-12 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr, 1883-01-04 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr, 1883-12-20 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Charlie Kerr, 1884-01-05 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Samuel M. Duncan, 1885-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to "My dear General", 1894-05-17 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Fitzhugh Lee to Eliot Danforth, 1898-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - George Washington Custis Lee, 1862-12-26 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - George Washington Custis Lee to Thomas F. Balfe, 1871-05-10 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - George Washington Custis Lee, concerning Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh's estate, 1875-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - George Washington Custis Lee to Harry C. Hines, 1876-09-30 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Thos. E. Marshall, Jr. to Edmund R. Cocke, 1893-09-04 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee, Lee, Mary Randolph Custis; Two letters appear laminated. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 1850s
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to "My dear Abbey", 1850-08-22 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to "Dear Brother", 1852-02-15 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee [to Mr. L.], 1859-02-11 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 1860s
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to Abbey L. Cook, 1865-01-27 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee [to Benson J. Lossing], 1867-06-12 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to "My dear Letty", 1868-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to Unknown, 1869-08-29 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to "My dear Miss Letty" (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 1870s
      - Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee to Unknown, 1873-09-16 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Note in the same pocket would appear to be from the 1870s. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mary R. Custis Lee to Mrs. Cocke, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Mary Custis Lee (daughter), concerning estate of A. M. Fitzhugh, 1875-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Mildred Lee to Preston Cocke, N.D. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Midred Lee to M. F. Maury, Jr., 1874-01-04 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Midred Lee to Mary, 1896-08-20 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Midred Lee to Elizabeth Cocke, 1881-08-25 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Richard Henry Lee to Patrick Henry, 1778-10-21 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Richard Henry Lee to Unknown, 1781-08-02 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Richard Henry Lee to Alexander Martin, 1785-01-04 (Box 1, Folder 58A)
  - Richard Henry Lee, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Robert E. Lee, Jr. to Edmund R. Cocke, 1866-01-14 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Robert E. Lee, Jr., concerning estate of A. M. Fitzhugh, 1875-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Robert E. Lee, Jr. to E. R. Cocke, 1913-03-01 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Robert E. Lee, III to Edmund R. Cocke, 1913-03-17 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Robert E. Lee, III to Edmund R. Cocke, 1914-10-31 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - William Henry Fitzhugh Lee to Custis Lee, 1852-02-15 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, concerning estate of A. M. Fitzhugh, 1875-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Photographic scrapbook relating to Robert E. Lee, N. D. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - George Washington Parke Custis to L. Littlejohn, 1817-06-23 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - George Washington Parke Custis to Philip R. Ferndale, 1830-03-12 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - George Washington Parke Custis to "Dearest Wife & Daughter", 1839-09-16 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - George Washington Parke Custis to William Seward, 1850-03-15 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Custis, George Washington Parke to Henry E. Wise, 1850-10-15 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - George Washington Parke Custis to Benson Lossing, 1855-12-02 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Custis, to Henry Winder At National Theatre, N.D. (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Mary Lee Fitzhugh Custis to "My dear Lucretia", N.D. (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Letters, 1797-1891 (Box 2)
  - P. G. T. Beauregard to I. Frank Howe?, 1865-12-22 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - P. G. T. Beauregard to Laure Beauregard Larendon, 1879-04-02 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - P. G. T. Beauregard to Judge Alf. Roman, 1882-10-25 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - P. G. T. Beauregard reply to John L. Manning, 1861-05 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Thomas N. Burwell to Edward Carrington, 1810-06-12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teller's Receipt, First National Bank of Alexandria, Va., 1865-08-07 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Will of Mrs. A. M. Fitzhugh, 1873-09-05 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - D. I. Markey to Benjamin Hallowell, 1851-04-10 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Ayers to Benjamin Hallowell, 1851-04-17 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin Hallowell to Robert W. Miller, 1873-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - D. H. Hill to Hon. John W. Ellis, 1861-06-16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jed Hotchkiss to his wife, 1873-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gen. Edward Johnson to S. C. P. Mitlan, 1862-01-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gen. Edward Johnson to Col. Johnson, 1861-08-06 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lt. J. E. Johnston to "Captain", 1841-09-08 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gen. J. E. Johnston to Maj. Gen. Jackson, 1862-05-27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gen. J. E. Johnston to Maj. Gen. Wilson, 1866-02-04 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gen. J. E. Johnston to Prof. J. L. Cabell, M. D., 1870-07-30 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gen. J. E. Johnston to Col. C. H. Andrews, 1874-12-09 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "In Memoriam. Gen. Joseph E. Johnston," Sermon by Rev. A. T. Porter, D. D., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Margaret Junkin to Mr. Sartain, 1852-02-11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Margaret Junkin to Mr. Sartain, Jan. 14 (no year) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "For Sarah Ann" from "My brotherinlaw, Wm. P. McKune", 1850-09-15 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Nellie" to "My dear little sister", 1874-08-08 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - E. F. Paxton to Samuel I. Campbell, 1863-04-27 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Frank Preston to Unknown, 1797-07-08 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rockbridge County Election Record, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gen. Winfield Scott and others, battle orders to Commander/Capt. Dahlgren, 1861 and N.D. (Box 2, Folder 17)